welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
okay there you go all right great
stop interrupting me okay
all right so yeah last time we kind of
talked about what the metagame
meant for each of us and it's a concept
that is evolving in people's heads
organically
people have different conceptions of
what it is um
one of the founder of the store peter
she talks about coming into right
relationship with ecology of games that
we're currently playing
and i really like that that concept of
right relationship i think it's at the
core
of what we're getting at here and so
i i guess i would like to build on that
and
so i i conceive of the metagame as
knowing which tools to use
how and when to use them and knowing how
we want to put them down
and i think this last part is a
fundamental to
right relationship uh we talked about
this is something we also talked about
anyway you've heard of this book by
this gentleman eric from hands in the
chat anybody no
okay yeah david do i okay
escape from freedom but oh okay yeah
yeah this one is i think is might be
more popular than that one but
escape from freedoms is popular too
um so we just went through anybody
wanted to give a recap of what
i guess this book is about and what we
talked about anybody
just anybody
wait
one second say something sure
sure i wouldn't want to recap it but i
just felt it was sort of a
complicated way of talking about being
self-centered or being compassionate
sorry i thought it was simply uh
the dichotomy between being
self-centered
or being compassionate it would be more
simple
put it that way okay interesting
yeah and another thing that a lot of
people brought up is that
it's not so much the particular thing
that's being done but the intention
behind it that's kind of related to
having right relationship to it
um it's about
choosing instead of allowing something
to choose for you
um so yeah we talked about that a lot
uh you know we really showed examples of
where it shows up in different
situations different books people
have talked about these things uh
through over time
throughout the time and religions kind
of call ideology when you're
when you're operating in the having mode
so sorry i have
some people who weren't here i guess
generally speaking the having mode is a
way
eric from talks about a way of being in
the world that
where you um
you're acting from an acquisitive uh
existential mode so you this is why you
use a bunch of this cluster of words
here to kind of give you a sense of what
the having mode is um
so possessing consuming idolizing these
things
are a kind of way to have a kind of
wrong relationship with certain
stimuli in the world and student objects
in the world
and it's more reactive than responsive
it's more
it's less of having a choice and being
chosen for
um so he talks about how you know the
advertising industry
encourages to confuse these two modes so
so they try to convince you that in
order to be in order to
express your creativity you need certain
things you need to have certain
status symbols certain uh products and
etc and this kind of modal confusion
um is is kind of prevalent in the
consumer society
so it's something that we have to
contend with almost every day
um so yeah we talked about specific
examples different
in different texts and different
traditions um
yeah so then we had a breakout session
this is one of my best friends
he always used to um advocate having
creative desires or possessive desires i
thought that was very related
and we had a breakout session talking
about
um talking about our own
uh possessive desires our own creative
desires and how they're related
and i think this is where we we stopped
this is where we left off
because i'm going to continue this this
process and then we'll have a couple
more breakout sessions
and hopefully we'll get we'll get to the
end this time
um so yeah anybody has
often is familiar with uh extended
cognition
or uh the concept of extended cognition
no no not really so uh extended
cognition is just the idea is that we
we think through or with tools so we use
thinking tools whether it's uh physical
technologies
social technologies or
psychotechnologies or
and those things are kind of like a
amorphous sets that
sometimes things overlap in them but the
idea is that we we don't
uh we don't really think purely we think
through different things
think through a language we think
through different concepts we think
through institutions
and even think through like physical
objects
they form our ontology our our
apparatus for interacting with the world
so so they kind of um they're repo
if you study like media theory you'll
you'll hear people talking about
how these tools that we we use they kind
of re
redraw the boundary of the self right
so um any questions
any questions
i have a comment i remember hearing
something from a cognitive scientist
about how
when you hold a screwdriver your brain
models the
length of your arm as the to the tip of
the screwdriver yeah
so we're just like naturally geared to
extending the boundaries of itself
exactly yeah this is precisely what i
was getting at
and i guess you'll see further what i um
how am i thinking of how this develops
and yeah that's precisely what i was
trying to get out here
um so yeah so this can be a problem uh
this is what
confusion is you know uh genre he talks
about confusion being
uh fused with you being fused with and
here are some examples of some tweets uh
in my my
feed of i think a certain type of
confusion that happens
unconsciously it's without choice and
you kind of fuse yourself with the
tools that you're using so if you guys
could read the first one it says
i've adopted i've opted into a pretty
strict community
structure and schedule where my time to
engage with tech is significantly
reduced
i feel like part of my brain has been
cut off like i've been lobotomized
really struggling to get back to analog
when i was 90 digital
tips to adapt so basically the idea is
that this person
got through usage of this of these tools
of this
uh medium kind of got fused with it got
confused with it
and um the person felt like
they lost part of themselves when you
hear people say i can't live without
this thing
it's a kind of accumulation of
attachments that happens naturally
and a problem with this is that
uh when these attachments get attacked
and we feel like
our we ourselves are being attacked
because we drew our boundary around that
thing
so whether it's like an ideology or like
in the second example you can see
you know i this says i can live without
the nba or the mlb
but i can't flip without the nfl so the
the person arbitrarily drew the boundary
of themselves around the nfl
and when that gets threatened they feel
they feel threatened and you can
extrapolate
the political ideologies or even things
in your objects in your life
like a car or something like that um
so you guys are familiar with this
experiment where uh
just show of hands people are familiar
with this experiment it's
it's pretty famous here um anybody want
to give a shot at
explaining it i think i want to
encourage you guys to
help me out here
oh everyone who raised their hand i want
one person to
try to give uh yeah
um i think it's like
so when he hits
the fake arm his he'll react
as if as it like is an internal
experience he'll react as if that's
actually hurting him
because i guess
the boundary like his mind
sees that fake hand as his real hand
and kind of reminds me of like you know
like when people don't have like get
their arm chopped off or something they
still have those phantom
sensations or whatever yeah
no yeah that's that's that's that's
precisely it
and um prior to prior to that experience
of feeling like your your arm has been
intact
they kind of stimulate it um you have
experienced stimulation with it so it's
like a
the more you mediate yourself uh through
an object or
perceive to be mediating yourself
through an object the more you get
attached to it kind of like
naturally our brain kind of does that so
yeah that's a really good
thank you matthew thank you
um i won't play the video because you
guys
you guys um matthew did such a good job
of explaining it
well does he freak out oh yeah he does
he does okay um you don't have to i'm
just curious
oh okay okay but you get you can you can
check it out but yeah he
he kind of uh feels like only that arm
pulls back he feels like
his arm was being attacked and you know
yeah
and it's it's a very repeatable
experiment it doesn't work all the time
but
you might want to try it out with your
friend maybe
um
all right so we're going to do a
breakout session um
i want to know you guys might want to
talk about like
how have you experienced this kind of
confusion
you know fused with something
unintentionally you know
you lose something all of a sudden you
feel like you lost your world
um and maybe about how you navigate this
problem
and maybe we can break out for about
five minutes around this and
you guys could come back and share what
you guys talked about
um so i'm just gonna stop sharing my
screen for a second here so i can split
you guys up
um
maybe i'll do three three people each
room
so yeah we got some new people who just
entered andre and manus who just
showed up while everyone's in the chat
uh
breakout rooms um
yeah anybody want to share what you
talked about
uh we we had an interesting chat about
instruments
and relationships and uh
actually julie if you want to share i
really like the way you described
your piece um i can say it too if you
don't want to share but i'd like to hear
from you
i can share um i was talking about the
last breakup that i had with my
boyfriend
my den boyfriend and i was remembering
our last night together as a couple and
the following night when i was
at my new place by myself and i could
feel like um i could feel like part of
myself was like shutting down
kind of like a computer is shutting down
and then the first night at my new place
i could feel that i'm rebooting with
different elements of myself
and there were certain applications that
weren't there certain parts of my
identity that wasn't there
that i had to rebuild
that's extremely interesting that that
analogy with the
applications that that's very salient to
me right now
yeah and i think as we go on the
presentation it can become
obvious why but yeah that's
that's really interesting even that you
had any kind of awareness to
to perceive that happening in yourself
it's really interesting
um anybody else want to share or ron
uh just one fundamental maybe thing we
came up with and shout out to matthew
for this
is that this is mostly an unconscious
process that
obviously we could maybe consciously or
when we're smart to say yeah the
screwdriver is not part of my
arm but the idea is that at some level
your unconscious
is making it and it could be the same
with lots of stuff so it's not even
knowing that we're
identifying or making part of ourselves
computers phones
again shout out to matthew used a good
example of driving a car and we all know
how
our unconscious can drive the car while
we're not paying attention
uh in a sense so it's makes it a
trickier thing if we don't even know
these processes are refused
so to speak yeah exactly
i mean and i guess people will get to
this
later on too but i guess that's why we
kind of developed different rituals
um to kind of shut down those apps
that you know we don't realize are
running in the background
um yeah that's that's really good share
thank you
um anybody else
yeah with the car analogy i just struck
me that i've had experiences with
where someone else was driving my car
and i was in the passenger seat
and it was very uncomfortable the car
was not stopping
as quickly as i would make it stop it
was because the person was not driving
exactly the way
that i would drive my car and it felt
very uncomfortable because
the car is normally a part of me
well that's a really interesting
anecdote that i never
i i never had a car so i didn't
experience it but i
yeah well that's really interesting
it's almost like you feel like someone
come in their party or
your system interested
any any oh paul you want to say
something
paul you're you're a meatball
oh i wanna meet you okay
it didn't work um there should be one
day when i
at best friend electronics from the
phone in the computer
like the sabbath you know yeah and i
mean i would really you know be
spiritually
[Music]
is one of the examples of people
attempting to kind of
put put their tools down and remembering
um the kingdom to come
you know the being mode the supreme
being mode yes
exactly okay so i will continue the
presentation
it unless anyone else has would like to
share
okay i just want to say on the topic of
the
car um i've had that dream symbology
happen to me
a lot of the time so it's it's not
uncommon at all
um yeah i think a symbolic of a lack of
control
yeah yeah excellent
okay let's see where to
leave off uh
yeah so can you guys see my screen
sure can okay perfect yeah so great
thank you um so yeah i just want to
bring up so
now we're getting on to the the uh the
topic of you know
what can be done about it and this is
something i want you guys to um
help me figure out and i want to hear
your feedback
but if uh how many years guys are
familiar with john vibacky
and his his uh awakening from the
meeting crisis series
so a couple people okay so so
so an episode in episode nine he talks
about the distinction between
uh meditation sorry yeah episode nine he
talks about
a distinction between meditation and
contemplation so
he suggests that um all of the ways
through which we try to apprehend
reality
apparently the world can fall on this
kind of uh
these two these two axes and one is the
opacity
transparency axis and one is the gestalt
features axis so stick with me here
oh i try to tie this back in
so the gestalt features access
is pretty much like if you if you
considered
um pointillism the style of painting
pointillism
you realize that if you zoom into the
picture you
you you get a a sense of what the
features are
each thing is a point on its own but
then if you step
back you get us the bigger picture and
you see
uh houses and other forms
emerge so this this this um
[Music]
this shift from features to gestalt
um is one was one of the dimensions
that we kind of um move through the
world with
and the other one is opacity
transparency is the difference between
looking at and looking through or
apprehending and apprehending through
so if something is opaque to you you're
looking
at it or you're interacting with it
directly
your cognition is interacting with it
directly but if it's
if it's transparent to you looking
through it and sometimes you forget
that you you you have it on like your
glasses is a perfect example
or an ideology you could be looking at
the world through an ideology
but not at you know you're not
you're not realizing that you're doing
that so that shift is something else
that
another axis along which we apprehend
the world
so his distinction between contemplation
and meditation is that it happens
on this kind of diet you know so
meditation is
going in into the self into the self
looking at
the features making them more opaque to
you so you focus on sensations you focus
on
uh different parts of your your
sensations and you're kind of going back
into your your yourself to
make make those things about yourself
opaque
and contemplation he says is the
opposite of that in in the direction of
um you're reaching out into the world
for meaning
and you're looking at the bigger picture
and you are you
going deeper and deeper into reality
through different to different
uh media and i really like this
distinction
um and i encourage you to look at the
the episode nine of his awakening
community
crisis i think it's a really useful way
to look at it i know
we can talk about it some more um so
so i so
how do we well one of the questions we
had the breakout session was
what do you do about this proclivity to
kind of accumulate
attachments accumulate things and i
think
i i want to introduce this term called
ontological breathing
so the ideas is kind of straightforward
i think
you might have guessed it by now it's
just um
oscillating between contemplation and
meditation
and so that you don't have apps running
inefficiently in the background so the
idea is that
um you put your tools down through
meditation you observe
your biases and your your tools that
you're using your attachments
you contemplate you you meditate on
your attachments and you kind of put
them down you make a decision to put
them down
and that affords you the resources to to
then
reach the contemplative heights that
give your life um
a sense of meaning a deeper meaning give
you the
the skills of apprehending reality
with high fidelity uh so you talk so you
hear
people from religious uh religious
backgrounds to
you know scientists talking about um
reaching transcendental
hype through the contemplation you know
einstein or
eric weinstein or
the the church fathers many many
centuries ago so
um so so the idea is that the
inspiration
is you know using the analogy of
breathing inspiration is
you're getting you inspired from the
world so you you you
up you go further into reality
expiration of self is you kind of
getting rid of the
you dropping the applets that are
running on in the background
you're dropping the attachments and
you're expiring that
um and
so yeah if you you look at these
self-worth nexus
it's almost like you're you're gathering
you're gathering of resources
to to kind of have to to apply them
to apprehending reality in a in a more
effectual way
um so yeah the bottom the bottom section
is just
what i think i ten what i think we tend
to
to how we i think we tend to be more so
often we kind of just have these
uh random attachments that we're not
sure we're not we're not aware of
um whether it's different um
ideologies different ideas different
models in which we
um or narratives stories we tell
ourselves i think
uh paying attention to stories that
you're telling yourself and
and who you think you are in that story
i think that's really important
so uh this is one way i've come to think
about
how to maintain the kind of healthy
um because we kind of have to use tools
right we kind of we obviously have to
use tools
so kind of ritualizing putting them down
so that
we can pick them back up again in a more
effectual way
it's almost like trying to play tennis
if you're having a
spatula it's like a frying pan in your
hand you have to put them down
to pick up the tennis racket so that you
can play properly
but i want to know if if this
conceptualization is
useful or makes sense to anybody or um
any tips on how i can think about this
in a better way or if anybody's heard a
better way of thinking about this we'll
have more breakup sessions but
yeah um i have one so if this is
if this is ontological breathing when
you refer to tools
what are you referring to because tools
and equipment
have a very definitive purpose
within ontology okay so
maybe you've talked about that more like
what do you mean
so within phenomenology and ontology and
the works of herdigo
equipment and tools of things and
objects we um
interact with and their purpose
depends on their handiness and they're
ready if they're ready for hand or
if they are just present at hand and
that
defines whether they just simply an
object like dirt
or if they're a tool like a phone or
like a hammer
or simmer so if we just sort of think
about like our phones our computer
a book that's all in one sense so it's
like
equipment but if we're thinking in this
other sense
there are a lot of other things we have
to sort of disconnect from and
uh get rid of our attachment from before
we can get into the ontological
mindset that's what i think
so i guess um
how anybody else want to chime in on
that
i i guess the way i look at it
i i don't agree with your definition and
i think
contemplation is one of these concepts
you can contemplate yourself
doesn't that be average um
i wasn't disagreeing with that oh no no
i think he was disagreeing with my
not yours andre okay no no yeah that's
that's yeah okay i appreciate that
feedback
i was i was um i liked
john vicki's um distinction
and it's it's kind of like all models
are kind of wrong
uh sometimes they're useful um but yeah
thanks for that feedback
um so sorry um yeah i
also just um discussing this and showing
this
uh it brought up ideas from
uh alchemical cognition i think is the
phrasing
of uh you know how
breaking out of the box thinking out of
the box using
ways of ways of you know cognitive
approaches
um that seem counterintuitive
and in that something that's interesting
is that in ritual
even the taking up of tools and the
laying down of tools
themselves can be rituals and or
meaningful themselves
and could themselves be contemplative
states or meditative states
um so i think that's maybe something
interesting to explore
so that it doesn't necessarily become a
not not that i think that that's what
you were saying but you know just
looking at a 2d picture it almost seems
like
there's this you know let's go up to the
state as a goal let's go
you know then down again to that state
as a goal but even
seeing the process as
uh maybe not maybe not as a journey to
the destination but actually as
processes themselves and the transition
itself
having properties that might be unique
to the transition yeah
that might be different from you know
yeah then one transition state so yeah
no yeah i totally get it
yeah it's like not not you
maybe not so much you're looking at
these things as like
end states but pretty in particular but
the journey through them the rituals
that
um shape the journey from one to the
other
in itself is an important uh thing yeah
i like that um
but yeah so i i just like the i guess a
simple
way to look at this is like you know to
a hammer everything looks like a nail
so if you want to apprehend the world
properly you kind of have to put the
hammer down and
maybe pick up some other tools but
anyway
so let's so the the idea that
so the idea that you kind of have to
kind of learn how to die you know that's
an
old very old classical uh philosophical
concept
and i just really like uh this gentleman
here at kona west anyone know conor
west yeah some people okay i love this
guy
so but yeah basically um you know he
says
you can't talk about truth without
talking about learning how to die
because it's precisely about learning
how to die
examining yourself and transforming the
old self interval so that you actually
live more
intensely and critical critically and
abundantly so the idea of like killing
killing the self is is is what i think
they mean by
putting putting tools down or putting
sorry putting the conceptions down that
your
your your attachments down
um and you know we talked about the
i want to know what you guys think the
difference but if if there's a
difference between contemplation
and meditation if there is just some
type of
semantics that's not useful i want to
hear what you guys have to say maybe we
can just
you know casually uh chat here
can you contemplate using an embodied
cognition you know through different
modes other than um
mental abstractions uh can you can you
contemplate with your hands i wanna i
wanna hear what you guys
um think about that you know you can
feel free to unmute yourself i
i think the first thing that came up
with this
um distinction um
the buddhist distinction between like
analytical
meditation and
i guess just meditation i forget the
names but yeah it's something like where
you use analytical
meditation to just sort of contemplate
something and then maybe
get a sense of that thing as a felt
sense and then you can meditate on that
felt sense to kind of
like dye your soul with it so to speak
yeah yeah that's what you're saying so
you kind of use kind of both in in
relation to each other to
to kind of supplement each other yeah
any anybody has ever thought about this
thing this distinction before
and if so does it how do you make sense
of it
something that came up for me uh khalid
was
maybe a bit of like a metaphor or
analogy is that
uh something like
when you're talking about the meditative
state it's almost like creating a space
right it's about that kind of
approaching a state of nothingness right
like putting the tools down
so it's more about the space than the
thing you use the space in and then
contemplation is
that place where the focus is on the
thing you use within the space
so both the thing and the space is
important because that creates the
situation the context
and it's the relationship between the
two that maybe there's kind of like a
hidden dimension to it
because there's a relationship i don't
know if that makes sense it's just what
came up i don't know if
any of that fits the question
no yeah i i kind of i you know it's
interesting as because
what you did with both of your shares
because you kind of
added that dimensionality to what we're
talking about which is
extremely very cool i like it
um but yeah the relationship it's itself
is
is like a another
optimization problem to use uh
you know that it's in itself it's a
challenging thing yeah i think it can
help describe
it from a perspective from a new
perspective right it can describe
the relationship can be perspective to
describe contemplation
from and committed you know meditation
yeah from as well
yeah yeah i've got an idea on that
definition so when we meditate
we try and connect to the ethereal plane
or
sort of another dimension and other
things arise mystically and then we
focus on them and let them go but when
we contemplate
we try and grasp onto things that come
from the ethereal
and then not let them go we focus on
them consciously and examine them
but then we have the choice to let them
go if we want
yeah wanting to build on top of that um
that's a major distinction that i see
with contemplation it seems that you're
creating a reality and really holding on
to it within
your um when whatever space you're
contemplating
and meditation is the opportunity to
take that all apart and take a look at
the individual pieces
yeah that's that's generally in line
with my my thinking
and i think um as has been brought up
here i think
you you kind of have to obviously
do both to do it um
to kind of enrich your life and to to do
them uh
maybe to contemplate deeply you kind of
have to learn how to
to to meditate or
maybe it's not not necessary maybe some
people are just talented and can
can do it but i feel like it it helps
that
it helps out a lot
well anyway so we maybe we'll do a
breakout session i want to
i want to know i want to source you guys
to figure out what
um you know do you get
engaged in any meditative practice
contemplative practice
and are they related for you in any way
i want to hear my experiences but
i'm going to break you guys out and
maybe you can come back with some
juicy stuff for me welcome back people
excited to hear what you guys talked
about anybody you want to start
share first
i'm gonna i'm gonna call on someone
i'm going to call on megan okay
we uh we got to an interesting topic uh
right at the end
about um the idea of sort of doing doing
activities as simple activities
and possibly sort of self-caring
activities
um in a meditative or a contemplative
state um
so andre was talking about um the idea
of sweeping as a
zen meditation practice
and i added to that the idea of um doing
the dishes as a meditative practice
um there's a there was a phase when i
was feeling really frustrated that i had
to do household tasks and i didn't have
enough time to meditate
so um and obviously feeling frustrated
and not having enough time to meditate
is very
counterproductive if you're trying to
you know cultivate
quality meditation um so
it was really useful to realize that you
know it's possible to cultivate that
meditative and or contemplative state
while doing activities um you know
walking the dog or
doing your laundry um whatever you're
doing especially if it's
if it's sort of angled towards some kind
of self-care um
then it's it's actually really valuable
to to be cultivating that kind of
state we didn't get as far as to
distinguish between the meditation and
the contemplation while doing one of
these activities
but um and maybe someone else has
something to do with that
yeah thanks for sharing
anybody else wanna piggyback on that
john
oh maybe he was saying bye
um yeah uh i guess one relation i've had
with it
and um i sometimes like thinking about
things
uh um with like um
you know like really like like the
layman and the master
like i don't know sometimes i just i i
like to think about both but like one
big thing is it's just a fucking break
from the contemplation i don't know i
guess i think of you know
even like the thoughts racing in my head
as like a version of
you know light contemplation but that
like can go on
unchecked for like 24 7. so at points in
my life i've even just been like
it's just you know just like it's nice
to know that
it's a break but at points though when i
realize it's a break it helps to shape
that
it's not your reality because one reason
why i think people should meditate more
is i think there's
hundreds of thousands of people probably
in the united states who don't even
realize that they're thinking in words
and like i don't know it's just like a
cake of mine but like that
that is shaping their reality and like
meditation at least shows you like
not that there's this like light at the
end of the tunnel but like
it's possible not to be like that all
the time
you know and that's a good makes it
the relationship with the contemplation
healthier i guess
yeah yeah yeah
yeah but yeah that's why i wanted to
kind of keep
it on the same continuous as
as you said like you your mind is racing
but as you said at the end um knowing
that you can
control that better makes it more
effective when you decide to actually
pursue one of the threads in your head
yeah
excellent um
can i just just double click on the um
on how you said
like controlling the thoughts in your
head um that was an idea that i started
off with
um and i think like having that idea
that you're
you know the practice of meditation is
practicing controlling your own mind
um i decided after a while about it
actually been quite like that had been
quite an unhelpful framework that i'd
been working in
um because i wasn't very successful at
controlling my own mind
um just just to clarify when i said
control i was
i was talking about the contemplation
side but
but i don't know if it makes it it's
meaningful distinction or not but
anyway yeah i feel like it's still
still relevant like um i guess uh it's
it's a slightly it's a slightly
different idea that i
that i had which was that you know by
practicing meditation i'm practicing you
know forcing my thoughts to all shut up
for a little while so i can meditate you
know
um but it's this it's the same idea if
you're
if you're contemplating versus
meditating whether there's thoughts in
there um
that's the distinction we're kind of
playing with at the moment
um but the idea
the idea i came to is that you can
practice
um you can practice you know recognizing
your thoughts
or understanding your thoughts or um
seeing your thoughts all of those things
which is not the
same dynamic as controlling them or
suppressing them or forcing them to do
this or that
um and if well i found that if i start
with that
that different angle on you know what
i'm doing with my thoughts
when trying to meditate um that
well it became a much more positive
process the whole thing
um and i found i don't want to say like
successful but i found i was much more
successful at it
with that with that basis and that
framework in there no yeah
i guess the um the idea of control
is is co is consonant with the having
mode that we talked about in the
beginning the having word rather than
being modest
the being always kind of yeah yeah so
that's thank you for bringing
up that back to everyone's attention
um we have well yeah we're kind of over
time but i want to hear
if anyone else has um thoughts there's
so much
stuff in the chat going off of anyone
else
before one of the things that um
you know that came up during chatting
about the questions is
that you know you get different forms of
meditation
or different approaches to meditation
different frameworks of meditation and
you know perhaps uh that might be
generally more well understood because
it's language for that these books on
that
but contemplation for at least me
personally
i'm not sure how to think about it in
different ways and different styles and
different approaches
and that's i guess simply because i've
never
looked at i've never thought about the
idea even that there might be different
ways of contemplating right
whereas different forms of meditating
our case came up because of
exactly what you know megan was
explaining there you know based on a
person's experience
you know different ways of approaching
meditation can can work and
also i guess depending on the person for
different purposes um
so that's something interesting to
explore like uh so if we discuss ideas
of
of meditation and contemplation it would
be kind of
from more from speaking from a
preference right
as a person like what how i understand
meditation because of my preferred way
of meditating and the same with
contemplation
so there might be a whole
domain to discuss in contemplation with
different facets and approaches and the
same with meditation and that would
put a completely different you know
angle on the whole conversation
um and another thing is i think
it's clear from your presentation that
there's an like a
this idea of some kind of
maybe i don't know a passive state
meditating and
more active state contemplating or at
least from the
what everybody was sharing it was this
idea of you're actively doing something
when you're
contemplating and it's kind of you like
trying to let go when you're
meditating that idea but another thing
that i noticed
when we were discussing this is that my
it's like my brain
doesn't just switch between an active or
passive mode but also between an
output and input mode like when
contemplating it's almost like you're
creating an understanding of something
right you're building something in your
mind
centered focus around a topic so you're
generating something
whereas if you're meditating it feels
almost like you're
opening it it's a place you can you can
open yourself
up to almost like ideas coming to you in
a sense
so it would kind of be more like how you
know dreaming would work
you know like daydreaming like you know
you kind of drift off maybe
and i'm not you know meditation is
brought okay this is maybe just one
experience of it whereas contemplation
is
is the idea of focus not not broad but
maybe depth
um so those are those are some
interesting
things came up oh yeah
oh sorry all right good please yeah what
you're
talking about they really thought up a
lot for me um
i think yeah for the contemplation part
was
um really intriguing and i think
um you know i see a couple ways of then
thinking about contemplation
you know from what michael osgood was
saying was sort of you know
just like how it's just thinking and
then
um man who's menace what you're saying
um and then
relating it to like how i would
personally describe contemplation um
distinct from thinking um and how
like for me i would
for me i like to think of contemplation
as like when i read maybe like a wisdom
book or something and there's just like
a little sentence in there
where it's just like there's like a
feeling it's like a feeling intuitive
sense where i'm trying to like
so it's it's a bit thinking but it's
also kind of like
like what what it's
for me i want to add that whenever i
totally get that
and whenever it happens i feel like
that's the only thing i remember
the whole book or the chapter is that
like
no yeah that's that's that's exactly
it's very very difficult concept
to grasp it's not exactly like thinking
but it's it's you know
it's reaching out for meaning like i'm
just being receptive to anything i'm
like searching for meaning
yeah um i just want to say one thing
like we have to wrap up but
i want to say that um daniel
he he runs the metagame mastermind and
he invited me to kind of
um kind of um run a session
and try to kind of like source you guys
for ideas and how to live a better life
a bigger life and
because it's a mastermind thing i think
he would be really happy if he
one of you guys maybe i know you guys
are really wise and really smart
i talk to you guys all the time so i
know so if you guys wanted to present
something or had an idea
i think he'd be really happy if you
pitched it to him and and he would give
you that space and
you know we can you guys can have the
same type of experience that
i've had over the past few weeks so yeah
that's just
open invitation from him because i spoke
to him about this before so
yeah keep that in the back of your mind
if you want to test some things out
learn from other people in a more
directed way
so yeah um um that's all i have time for
but uh feel free to stick around um
and hope to see you guys next week as
well
yeah thanks for co-hosting this doing it
was great
thank you thank you thanks
thank you thank you
thank you now i'm going to be alone here
okay
were you guys hanging i heard him say
hang if you want so i didn't know if
that meant the room would just stay
in case it did
but i don't want to stay alone so that
would be weird yeah
i can do a little yeah i'm just trying
to work out yeah
i i think you gave the host to yeah
manny
and of course it's it's what time for
you andre you know i always like to ask
that
9am okay oh that's not too bad i was
thinking it was like seven
no it's because i had to spend all night
doing
and finishing off an assignment